I call it over the writer's government in the city council from Monday April 1st, 2024.
Two proclamation declaring April, 2024 is autism awareness.
They accept it tomorrow.
Motion to approve.
Second.
Hi.
Eastern.
Williams.
Hi.
And nobody's here for that, right?
Three.
Input.
Let's get a personal picture as we have one.
I'm just going to weigh you brown.
Hey, Parker.
Thanks for having me in council.
Just wanted to come here in person and offer that the important family stands ready to assist
and do the fund, the purchase of the surplus piece of property, which affects our property on the lower
land.
We would propose that we would put up the funding city, we would purchase it from the city,
basically the sign of the council.
However, then everyone can work out the agreements.
Best to get the full kind of fit in the site design, traffic circulation and everything else.
We've worked about eight years getting about 2016 to get this point.
We've won two lawsuits against ODOT, which helped force the issue to make the property declared
as surplus.
The blue shaded part on the survey is what the state took from us in 1956.
The orange is the right away.
It was really part of the blue as well.
Going north of the created 69A, the yellow is what they just recently took from us, which is
about the same size as the parcel that they've offered to the city.
We think that it was offered in air to the city, but we want to work with y'all to the
bedroom of the city to create sales tax revenue for the people here in Miami.
And we think that that site really needs that front footage to maximize the value.
And so we're here to stand ready to fund it, to work with the city on anything to do with utilities with.
signage for the betterment of the city and the maximization of the revenue for the city.
So that's why I came in tonight, would appreciate doing this on the all schedule.
I know we've got 45 days from the day to the letter from the T.A. to the city.
Execute that and I'm sure they're amenable to working with y'all and we're certainly amenable to working with y'all
to facilitate it and get this development.
I don't know if you're interested in any questions anybody has or a section that's really designed for that.
I'll be here in town, if y'all need, we were in putter.
We've got lots of data that I could share with you, but you really want to get this property.
Starting work generates revenue for the city.
Thank you so much for being here.
For calling us.
Want to approve?
T.A.
Hi.
Five.
minutes from the March.
A level.
Twenty-twent-two.
A special meeting.
March.
Twenty-twent-twent-twent-twent-twent.
Twenty-twent-twent-twent-twent-twent-twent-twent-twent-twent-twent-twent.
I'm just kidding.
He's sad.
Hi.
Six presentation discussion.
The Mime Area Economic Development Services Incorporated Action Plan for Economic Development,
Mr. Shandu Han, and Mr. Jim Brown.
And hello, it's here too.
I don't really care how much she's part of that team.
She drives that team.
Let's be clear.
Mayor, thank you.
It's always in the great opportunity to come before the council and speak to you.
Especially when we get to talk about something that's important to all of us and that's economic development.
As you remember, back at the end of last year, the Mime Industrial Development, the Mime Area Economic Development Service,
contracted with Mr. Fram and his company, Community Growth Strategies to develop an economic development action plan for Mime and Ottawa County.
Mr. Fram has been working hard, conducting numerous interviews in person, zoom interviews, task force meetings, and he even held a public forum here at the Civic Center.
To gather information for the development of this plan, that data is what is led to the creation of this plan.
And so what I want to stress to you before I introduce Jim is, we need to make sure that just because the Mime Area Economic Development Service,
the Mime Area Economic Development Service,
in the creation of this plan, which was driven entirely to give credit where credit is
due by our chairperson, Ms. Heather Lillard, because I don't know that we would have gotten
to this point, I don't know we would have gotten this far without her leadership, but she
really helped drive this project and as a result Mr. Fram is put together, I think, a strong
plan. He's going to hit some of the highlights of that tonight, but remember this, it's
our plan, it belongs to all of us and it's only going to be a successful based on the amount
of effort that we're all willing to put into it. We're not here to take credit, we're not here
to make it any one believe for one second that this belongs entirely to Mades. We all share in this
plan and we hope that you'll join us because without it this plan cannot be successful. So with that
being said, please join me in welcoming Mr. Jim Fram from Community Growth Strategies.
Thank you, Shannon. May I remember the council? Citizens of Miami. We've been working on this
nearly seven months now. Excuse me, springtime allergies. And we've put together about a 30-page,
very detailed plan and I'm not going to sit here tonight and read a 30-page plan to you, but as Shannon said,
we're going to try to give you some highlights of this plan going forward and respond any questions that
you may have. The ultimate goal of this plan was to develop basically a to-do list.
A to-do list, not for Shannon, a to-do list, not for Mades, a to-do list for the community, because everybody
in the community needs to have some ownership in this strategy going forward and we've made some of
those assignments. So we'll go through this. Talking about the economy, they're primarily two
kinds of jobs that can be recruited to a community one of those as retail or service. The other one
is primary. Retail is a very important component of an economic development strategy that retail needs
one thing, customers. And those customers need one thing. Those customers need an income that gives
any ability to go buy purchase product or services from that retail business. So both of those are
very important. So we're going to be focusing on both types of jobs as we go through this community.
Shannon touched on this, but it's important that we have a team. I've had the pleasure of being in a
professional economic developer for over 40 years now and I've worked in places like Little Rock, Tulsa,
Lincoln, Nebraska, but I've also worked in places like Bartlesville, Oklahoma, Harrison, Arkansas,
House Springs, Arkansas, Killing, Texas, and it's the same everywhere. It's successfully economic
development program is when that developer then investor.
or that site location consultant comes into town
and he sees that that community is kind of all going
in the same direction.
If they're fussing and fighting and lots of disagreement,
they've got lots of other places they can go
where people operate or work as a team on economic development.
So this plan encourages you to pursue that.
We did a lot of interviews.
We did a public forum.
We did some small focus groups.
But a lot of this plan too is driven by demographics.
In the report, you'll see two pages of demographic information.
There's a very detailed report for my alma.
There's a very detailed report for Ottawa County.
I'm just going to get some of the highlights of that.
Basically, in the last decade from 2021 back,
your population growth declined by nearly five percent.
So you get more people moving out than moving in.
One of the real good things in the demographic study
is a median age and your community is 32 years of age,
which is younger than the US average, younger than the national average.
Native American populations, nearly 20 percent.
The percent of people below the poverty line is 23 percent.
That's something we need to work on in change.
Nearly 30 percent of the population receive some
form of public assistance.
We need to do some things with this strategy to create good
paying jobs to change some of those things.
The first thing that we did was, I mentioned the public form,
the focus groups that we did in the interviews.
And these are some things that came out and are kind of listed in prior
re-order.
And I'm going to talk a little bit about each one of those.
The first thing that I can get my quick work here.
The first thing that came out and probably the most prominent thing
is no secret anybody was the flooding.
And we're going to talk about that as later as we go into this.
The second thing that in this strength, weakness,
opportunity analysis that people said is that we have a great location.
We need to take advantage of that.
We're nearly a suburb of Joplin.
We're less than 90 miles away from Tulsa.
If you draw a triangle with Northwest Arkansas Joplin Tulsa,
we're almost in the center of that center of that triangle.
So our location is very good.
And we need to sell that.
We need to take advantage of that.
We're sitting right on the turnpipe.
Thousands and thousands of cars go back and forth on that each day.
Let's get them all to turn and come in here and spend some dollars.
The next thing that talked about was quality alive.
People that attended this public forum and went to these focus groups
want to see the quality of life elevated here.
That's natural.
That's something wanted in every community.
Another one that was a big talking point with people
was affordable housing.
There's a housing shortage.
And we're going to make some recommendations further down
and report on how to address that.
The other one was crime and crime legislation without getting into detail.
there is some confusion and I'm glad to see the chief police here but there's some confusion
in first responders going to something about whether it's one of the Native American
Tribal units that needs to be responding or a city unit or county unit and there's some
state law that's kind of mixed up in that but that's something that came out in some of the
focus groups and some of the public comment and so we want to talk about that a little bit
as we go forward. Next one is Tribal Relations. One of the most important things you can do,
you've got a good relationship with the Native American Tribes here now. We need to continue
to develop that relationship and enhance that relationship and that's going to do nothing
but help your economy. There are some things that we haven't done in the past that we need
to do going forward where the Tribal folks can be great partners to economic development in this community.
The other one is obvious and you saw that the demographics people want manufacturing jobs or primary jobs.
They want high paying jobs. They want to pull out of that poverty. They want to get above that poverty line.
They want to be able to go and spend dollars at retail businesses and at service industries in the community.
The next thing was streets and this is a problem that's common with every city in the state, every city in the country,
as people want to see the streets improved and taken care of better as we go through.
The last one is industrial business park land and this is very important because it's product.
I don't know who said this quote that somebody said you can't sell from an empty wagon.
If you don't have products, you don't have anything to sell and that product needs to be business-developable land.
It needs to be industrial land and there's going to be some discussion as we go through this about possibility of a spec building.
You just fill one and so we need another one.
This is kind of put into three parts business-attack attraction.
Business retention taking care of businesses that we already have and entrepreneurship.
We want somebody that has a good idea to build a company to build that company here and not someplace else.
We're going to talk about business attraction first.
The first goal is to pursue the attraction of new primary jobs in my local home and surrounding region.
It's very important that we do that and there's some things that we're going to recommend that you do in that business attraction.
I mentioned earlier the importance of teamwork and everybody kind of going in the same direction.
But we need to have a point-person.
We're recommending a strategy that the CEO of May is that point-person.
The mayor has to be on the team.
You members of the Council have to be on the team.
Counting commissioners have to be on the team.
Everybody has to be on the team.
But you need a point-person that can direct the developer and the site location consultant and the person that's investing to where to go to get what information.
It's very, very important if a site location consultant comes into town and they've got to
go find 10 different people on their own, they're not going to stay here very long because
they have other options and other places to go, so we need that point person. That's our recommendation.
We're going to ask maids to identify the owners of a potential industrial and business park
plant. Again, that's product. We have some now. You always need more. You get contacts from the
utilities, you get contacts from open department of commerce, you get prospects that just come in
off the street, you have to have product to be able to show them. Despite building, you just
filled your spec building. And my first question was, or my first comment was congratulations,
my first question was, when are you going to build an exploit? Because if you didn't have that spec
building, that company wouldn't be here, it wouldn't have come in here. So you need to start working
toward putting together the next spec building to draw that person. I think you need to recruit retail
businesses. Your mayor has been very active in that, might just been very active in that. You need more
retail businesses because in Oklahoma City supported by sales tax revenue. So it's very important
that we build that. We're recommending that maids prepare a fact sheet on potential retail sites
in the community that include traffic counts, cost of property information that companies need.
Most, especially national companies, have a template that they use to decide where they're going to
put a store or where they're going to put a location. And that's usually based on traffic counts in front of
the sites. It's based on per capita income. It's based on household income. It's based on how many
people you have above or below poverty line. And like McDonald's for example, they built so many stores
across the country and around the world that they know what that template has to say to be profitable.
And they're not going to build a store in a location that the criteria doesn't meet that template
and doesn't make them successful. We're going to recommend, we're recommending that maids
develop online surveys. Let's find out what people in my and auto walk out here driving to
shop and what are they driving to tell us about? What are they driving to North West, Arkansas to buy?
Let's find out what those things are. And that gives Shannon and his team a list of the types of businesses
that we need to bring in because we can go to developer until that developer that we surveyed our
community and our survey, our survey has told us that these are the type businesses that this community wants.
We're recommending that maids join ICSC. That's an acronym for organization of retail developers
from across the country.
They have several forums or shows across the country.
The closest one to us here is called the Red River event,
and it's usually held in the Fort Worth area.
We're recommending that they may join that,
that they participate in that event every spring,
that they take a team representative from Miami to that,
that they go in armed with that template
with those demographics to talk about how many retail sites we have,
what traffic counts are,
what some of the demographics are of our community
to convince some of those developers to come take a look.
Marriage is very important for you and council members
to be a part of these teams as we go out and do this stuff.
So they know we have political leadership going forward and asked.
Go number three, we're recommending that we extend and recreate
an extensive marketing plan that supports and achieves the actions
of this economic development strategy for the surrounding region.
One of the things that we think you need is way finding signage.
In the report, I've got some photos of some other communities
that have very attractive way finding signage.
Some of them right here in Oklahoma.
But when somebody takes that exit off of the turnpike
who's never been here before, they need something that tells them
where the city hall, where's the chamber of commerce office,
where the schools, where the, where's medical care, that sort of thing.
They need to be directed down here to your beautiful main street
because if they just get off of that exit and buy gas
and get back on the turnpike, they're never going to see this beautiful street
that you have going up in 36.
So we're recommending that the city invest in way finding signage
to help make that happen.
But together a social media effort, this would be a joint effort
with the city and the schools, within a yo, with maids,
to have a social media effort to be on social media.
I have 40 plus clients in Oklahoma, Arkansas, Kansas, and Missouri.
And I can tell you that three or four of those who have developed
a strong social media presence are out front
and they're seeing every day and they're seeing by developers.
They're seeing by investors and they're seeing by site location consultants.
Benchmark against other communities.
Oklahoma has several communities that are doing a great job
in economic development.
They're also great organizations in surrounding states
that have been very successful in economic development.
I'm suggesting that Shannon put a few folks in a car
and go visit with these folks.
We all have egos.
They like to brag about what they're doing.
So let's go let them tell us what they're doing.
And if it's a good idea, let's bring it back to my main use it here.
I'm a huge believer in Benchmark.
Here's an example on a larger scale.
Tell us if there's one Benchmark visit every year
to a large metro area.
They take about 120 people.
business leaders from Tulsa to go on those and they come back and bring those ideas back and implement those there.
I'm recommending that Miami do that on a smaller scale because you're going to be looking at organizations, communities closer to your size.
Next, the second section of this three-pillar plan is business retention expansion.
And that's taking care of the businesses that you already have.
We're recommending that you design and create a robust BR&E program that provides assistance support for existing business employers.
In my opinion, an economic development world, even though we're out recruiting new companies in new industry and we're recording entrepreneurs,
taking care of those businesses that are already here, that are already employing people that are already making a payroll as most important work we do.
And we're asking Mades to get heavily involved in surveying those companies to know what's going on with them, to meet with them on a regular basis.
We're asking them to form an executive roundtable of plant managers that get together on a regular basis and compare problems and compare issues and challenges.
And what can happen a lot of times is this can create a identified crisis before it becomes a crisis, so there's something the community can do to assist and to help them going forward.
There's a classic example of that close to you here.
And if you're familiar with the ABB operation in Bartelsville, always several hundred people that's in their industrial park, that started as a small company spun off of Philip 66 was purchased by ABB and ABB was going to move it to Houston.
Bartelsville was able to build them a building, at least it back to them, and incentivize rate.
And they stayed there in Bartelsville with about 30 people. Well, today they've had three expansions, several hundred people working there, they're all six figure salaries.
And that's an example of what a good business retention expansion program can do.
We're going to ask Mades to maintain a database of local companies, who the plant manager is, what their product is, what their annual payroll is, what their annual sales are.
What challenges are they having? Is there something that the city can help them do? Is there something the county can help them do? Is there something that the Native American tribes can help them help them with?
The third leg of the of the stool is entrepreneurship, and I don't have to don't have to go very far to get an example on entrepreneurship.
Sam Walden worked for Ben Franklin stores in Newport, Arkansas, and Ben Franklin stores told him that his idea of discount merchandise was not really good to go back to work.
Newport didn't offer him any help, so he moved.
Bentonville, and guess where the headquarters of the world's largest retail company is, and
Bentonville, Arkansas. You can't make a case for that to be there. That headquarters is there
because that company was born there. So we're recommending that you do some things to give every
person in Miami and Ottawa County that has an idea about how to form a company or how to form
business, but to help them do that if it's something that's viable, it's helped them put that together
and maybe that turns into something larger. We're suggesting that Mades do a lot of partnership with
the chamber on this that they host a monthly coffee break for entrepreneurs for people who are working
on starting new companies. We're recommending that the Mades office building offers some shared
office space, maybe for somebody to just starting a company that needs some office space to kind of
kick start that company and get it going. We're recommending that Mades host a pitch contest at least
once a year. I hosted a pitch contest in Hot Springs five years. The first year was kind of rough.
We had about five people present companies and we had five local people that were judges. But as that
real year by year we started having venture capitalists show up and investors show up. We had people from
Dallas coming in standing in the back of a room to see what some of these company ideas were and dropping
some dollars. That's something that grows very, very fast. Mades has a revolving loan fund that is the
mean when I first moved into Oklahoma back in the late 90s, Mark Young was the, Mark Young was the
Shannon Doohan of back then and we were running the revolving loan program and it was the envy of every economic
development organization in the state. My understanding is that over the years that revolving loan
fund has been responsible for creating some 2,000 jobs. We're recommending that you market that
program, that you help a grow in any way that you can because that's very important to businesses that
they're here, whether they're primary businesses or retail businesses. Game changers,
game changers are things that are difficult to do, expensive, sometimes not politically popular,
but they're things that completely can turn the community in a way and we've identified some of those
and some of those are going to recognize because some of those ideas came from you. The first one we're
recommending is that chamber put together public policy committee that they form political action committee
and they begin to become engaged not an individual politics, not in personal politics, but in issue politics.
Identifying those issues that impact businesses, that impact employers and taking stands on those
and being sure that the elected officials, you all state representatives, state centers.
on after the governor's office and maybe even on federal level, understand that we're in the business of creating business and creating new jobs.
And we need to be sure that we're supporting those issues that help that happen in our community.
The next thing that we're recommending is the GRDA relationship, the flooding in Tyler Avenue,
and it's been a lot of time with you, but I spent some time with Beau and the city staff and the city, I think, has done a remarkable job in getting some female grants and doing some other things to raise some streets and doing some things.
And I kind of refer to it. I'll do respect, a pot of patching kind of to address that thing.
You've got a FERC ruling that we've copied into this report, and we're just basically recommending that you keep working on that relationship.
And it's interesting that we have public policy and the flooding and GRDA relationship close together because those are going to kind of go hand in hand.
And the chamber being a private entity and private nonprofit organization can help with kind of the politics of that.
And maybe helping our political leadership at the state federal level become a little bit more responsive.
Tribal Relationships are very important. When I was doing economic development for the Tulsa Chamber, we had five chiefs on our border directors of 20 people.
And it was very important. It was very impressive to you, investors, and they bring a ton of resources to the table.
In addition to the resources they already have, they have connections with resources, the Bureau Indian Affairs and other organizations in Washington that can be very helpful.
Do your effort going forward, so we're recommending that you continue to enhance and develop that relationship going forward.
Housing. We're recommending that the city engage in a housing study.
I'm not looking for business myself. I don't do housing studies, but I'm recommending that you do a housing study to find out.
Number one, if there is a shortage. Number two, what the shortage is.
Number three is the shortage. Big house of small houses, middle houses, where do they need to be?
This study can tell you all of these things. The things that you see happening in downtown Tulsa right now today are the result of a housing study that we did in 2009.
That said, that if you built off the apartments in downtown Tulsa, that the people that are in there late teens to mid-30s would move to downtown Tulsa.
And you're seeing that happen right now. That was a result of a housing study.
Your housing study probably needs to be fashioned a little bit different, which you need to find a housing study to find out how that works.
Then we're recommending that you look into doing a tax increment finance district.
And you all don't have two hours tonight, so I'm not going to explain what a tax increment financing district is, but it's a method of taking public funds.
and paying for infrastructure on a housing development,
which adds to the profit for the developer,
and it makes the housing development more attractive for the developer.
I said that real fast, I hope that made sense to everybody.
But we did one of those in Bartelsville for 110 houses,
four kind of co-philips, employees, workwork very, very well,
and I can give you some leads to go through that.
The next one is funding.
If you ask me one of the most successful economic development programs in Oklahoma,
I'm probably going to say, Enid, Pancasiti, Duncan, Bartelsville,
just to name a few, and they all have something in common.
They have a fraction of a sales tax dedicated economic development.
Sales tax collected by the city.
It's governed by a city appointed economic development commission,
but the funds are used by the companion organization,
to my which will be made to do economic development to fund the program.
We're recommending that you investigate the potential and the possibility of doing that type of funding.
Other game-changers product.
If you have land and you have the building and you have the way to get to it,
and you have the people that work, you just become very interesting
to site location consultants, to developers, to companies that want a location in the Midwest,
to companies that want to be on the turnpike, to companies that want to be between
Joplin and Tulsa, to companies that want to be between Oklahoma City and St. Louis,
you become very attractive to those.
But you've got to have a land, put them on, you've got to have buildings to put them in,
so it's very important that you pursue that effort that's putting that product together.
The last one, and certainly not least, is place-making.
Quality of life.
If you're going to have a workforce to work at those companies that you're going to be recruiting in here,
you have to be working on things like streets, housing, schools,
you have to do things that increases the quality of life and the community.
This was something that a lot of our focus groups, a lot of public forms,
told us that they were very concerned with.
One of the big things that's going on across the country now is biking and hiking.
Trails, bike lanes up and down streets, so people are,
especially that younger generation, the companies that are wanting to recruit to work.
That's the fastest growing thing with them.
This is my last slide.
No applause.
This is, these things are difficult today.
It's different.
It's things you've never done before.
As I said, I've done some 40 of these in the last five years,
and the ones that have been very successful with it are the ones that open that book.
And the pages are dog-eared, and there's notes written on them, and it's a working document.
The mayor has a copy, the member of the Council's have a copy.
Your state of representatives have a copy, leadership, and the community have a copy.
Your plant managers know what's going on.
There are various assignments made throughout this plan for each one of those folks.
And the way to be successful at it is to work the plan.
It needs to be a working document, and it needs to be a changing document.
It would be delighted to try to respond to any questions you may have or I'll turn it back over to you, Janet.
Thank you.
So, just to kind of recap some things real quickly, because I know you want to move on.
Everybody will go home before the storms hit, I'm sure.
The thing I found most interesting about Jim's plan is that there was a good mix of things that were already
we're talking about, and this just kind of confirms that we were on the right track with that thought process.
Some of these things were actually already working on, are already accomplished.
And then thirdly, it gave us some ideas and things that we weren't doing that we need to do to step up our efforts here.
Not just in my Emma, but in Ottawa County as a whole.
The main thing I encourage you now, so Jim's going to give a presentation to borrow the official public rollout of the plan.
That's at 530, and it's going to be in the ballroom here at the Civic Center.
We shared it on our page, the the mage page on Facebook, if you would be so kind, just to go and share that with your contacts.
We want to get as many people there as we can, so that we can give them an idea of what's in this plan.
Here are their questions, answer their questions, but more importantly, hopefully give people a chance that when they hear something in this plan, that it's really important to them,
that they may want to sign up and come on board and be a part of the team.
Because I'm not going to be able to do all of it by myself.
The chamber's going to help, but Cindy can't do it all by herself either.
The city's going to be a partner in this, but Blair, Mayor Bless Parker can't do everything by himself.
The council can't do it all.
You can't do it all by yourself. We have to work together.
And we need involvement from key people in the community. We need business leaders.
We need tribal leaders. We need citizens who just care about our community and want it to be successful to be a part of the process.
So encourage everyone you know to come out tomorrow for the public roll out at 530.
Get involved, ask questions, sign up to be a part of some of these tasks.
Because everything that Jim's outlining here, we're going to sign different committees or groups to drive those projects home.
We'll oversee it. We're working on a committee now that's going to kind of be the oversight committee for all of these.
For all of these, it's going to be a part of the committee.
going to hold all of those sub-drugs accountable.
We're going to provide some now-one when I come and make presentations to the City Council.
The first thing I'm going to do is update you on where we are on the plan.
That's going to be step number one.
Then we'll talk about other things and we'll do the same thing when we speak in front of any
other organization.
Thank you for your time.
If you have any questions, Jim and I would love to answer them, but we appreciate the opportunity
to be here tonight.
We look forward to seeing all of you tomorrow and if you have any questions by
all means, if you don't get the chance to ask them tonight, please ask those questions
tomorrow.
Thank you very much.
Hi, I'm 7.
Budget amendment number 24-12 increased carryover for $5,065.46 to the police department
fund and moved $3,161 on 17 cents to spend if needed.
You can spend the $550 or can they training credit from fiscal year 2223 increased carryover
by $6,780.4 cents for the drug forfeiture fund to actual and move the revised total
money.
It's available $81,633.4 cents to the proper expense accounts.
Move the home department of libraries, the adult online high school grant money is of $3,248.4
cents for number 300 grant donations fund to number one general fund for grant staff support.
Half was for fiscal year 23, 223 and another half for 23, 24.
There's a lot there.
You can do this very well.
What this does is two funds, it makes their carryover actual, because during the budget, I estimate
what the carryover is.
Well, this brings these particular funds to actual carryover.
I worked with high tower and his assistive Jera on that.
And the third thing is adult online high school, high school grant that the library has.
A portion of that goes towards salaries, so we're moving that from the grant donation fund, which
has been 300 and we're moving it to the general fund, which is.
Motion to approve.
Second.
All right.
Member and member and member of understanding with the Ottawa County Fair Board for use.
The Fairgrounds show bonds for fiscal year 24, 25.
That's it.
Good.
Great.
The MOU's will be this every year.
The first one is the MOU between us, the city and the county firm.
Nothing changed.
Motion to approve.
Hi.
Number nine.
Memorand and the better standing for the outstanding farmers market for 20, 24.
This one here is an MOU between City and the Auto County farmers market.
This one did have a change in it from last year.
This one has the addition of the Auto County farmers market.
We will be paying the electric utilities.
They do not have a change in the RFP.
This is because we added the poor farm and half ton of them.
Yes.
At least one of those will read that.
They will order the farm and half ton of them.
Much has been approved.
Second.
Can you stand?
Hi.
Ten.
Contract with Schneiders.
Sneakers.
That's our work.
So I'm 40 coming in amount of $20,000.
For the July 4th, 2020.
And again, this is between City and Schneiders.
Our work show.
I talked to him.
I talked to Lexington.
He's got.
He's just not too late to increase this.
I'm thinking about outside.
Outside help.
He says that every year.
Yeah.
He increases every year.
But last year.
Twenty.
Who's the accounts for a room in the afternoon?
I'll show you now.
Second.
Okay.
All right, well governing charter between the city of Miami,
co-opelination and the Ottawa County E911 governing authority for the Ottawa County
Emergency Communication Center.
This is the government document that covers the,
basically in the U with us, the co-opelination and the 911 board,
or running the dispatch center.
The staffs have sponsored those for all parties and guidelines and the staffs today at
the organization, because all of the spews,
uh,
Ben Loring, uh,
drafted this.
He represents city in the 911 board and, uh,
well, I was agreed to have them, uh,
drafted.
We've all worked on it together,
and then come up with this government,
the governor of charter.
Mr. Duper.
Uh,
question.
Bends it on trust land.
Can I just want this contract up eventually?
That is the, uh,
64,000 dollar question.
Thank you.
The answer is yes,
they could have tried to define this,
so that the pressures, uh,
the sentiments of the community would keep that in happen.
But, uh,
there is another fallback on that is the way this entire system is being designed.
We could take some of the
mobile computers that we have.
I know we spend a lot of money on this,
but it's still at the same time.
I feel like that this is a scary situation.
And I've said that all along.
I understand that sentiment and it,
it is, but we have, uh,
you know, the interest of public safety,
this is the entire county.
And I don't see that happening at all.
We've had a really good partnership,
but we're going to have a really good board of the group.
And, uh,
I would surprise me if anything like that.
Chief, it's, it's happened in days just all apart.
All parties there.
I mean,
and then they take, they take,
they get out.
They've been in jail for all of our party, so.
We're without the adequate size.
I think you can operate what we need.
Basically, the tribe is providing the facility,
providing the better part of the...
Good.
And software is the vacation.
and worst-lying new voids.
That point was where that board was.
Yes.
So that doesn't change what our responsibility in this area is.
Yeah, great to have you here tonight.
There's a possibility of a tornado threat, let me think there's a possibility.
We have the entire communication for auto-canning downstairs on the soft-cell at its time.
We've been marinated down the tornado of shelter at all.
So the opportunity to put that in a secure shelter so we can better maintain communications
for the entire county public safety is just a huge benefit, a move out there.
Well, I definitely get it.
I think it has been a bit to some point, but I also think it's a scary situation for us because
we have spent a lot of money.
We've been on trust land, I think that we could eventually get screwed.
There is a possibility right now a trust mark.
I get it.
I'm going to risk it to clean up all of these green-to-end vehicles, this is a lie blind to police and fire.
And if we don't have a place right here, do we?
I mean, we can, of course, but is it going to work properly?
I mean, the system is how it's glitched there, for instance, it's been called, but again,
it's how it would.
You guys test that kind of stuff on regular basis for doing table pops and what if scenarios?
I mean, you guys do that kind of stuff anyway, right?
I'm just the first part of that.
So we were talking about, we were talking about the backup system plan B if this goes south
for some reason.
And his concern is would that do we know if it work?
Part of this facility, we're putting on redundant facility downstairs, so we'll still
have the capability to dispatch emergency downstairs.
There's always a backup available.
And the remote capabilities of the new CAD software will actually be tested.
And everything's going to be tested before we move.
So yes.
And I'm talking about, like, on an annual or every other year.
Yes, we do have a territory.
Okay.
That's what I was at.
So if that building got to be in my nuclear war end, we can move back back here.
The ELC downstairs is still, we'll be set up with dispatch capabilities.
And it's been saying that the CAD software, the new program that the port bought, the number
of the board, is totally cloud-based, so they can log in for about...
anywhere and start.
All second motion.
No.
I.
13.
There's an nomination.
Three of point.
Ray van's using.
He's the amount of public library board.
Turned it's fire five five.
The point.
Motion.
Okay.
All right.
14.
There's an.
There.
Those.
Well.
All.
Turned it's.
Job.
Five.
sixteen.
Fifteen.
Eighteen.
zeron.
Fifteen.
So far we collected two men, 90,000, so we had the name to collect 6,700, 7,000, 6,000, 6,000, 6,000, 6,000, 6,000, 6,000, 6,000, 8,000, so we should collect in 12.28 months.
And that has been it on the weather, so my hope is, you know, as the summer reaches, the temperatures reach higher, that we should be able to collect faster on that.
So we've been at this for 21 months, so I think we've been going to find that staff jail and we've been really creating this time together.
So, just kidding, I don't know, it's on average utility bills and we get asked by it.
So, my team, this may be continued.
We've got a chamber to redevelop the staff room, the purpose of the big executive session.